In this world,
there's an invisible magic circle.
What?
There's inside and outside.
Capture the movement.
These people are inside.
And I'm outside.
But I don't really care.
How's it coming?
Let me have a look.
Oh, no. Are you okay?
Hey, hey...
I---
I hate myself.
Anna...
Oh, I'm so glad.
Thank you, Doctor.
Anna, do you feel all right now?
I'm fine.
Where was your inhaler?
I cost you money again.
Why do you say that?
Oh, Miyoko.
I brought Anna's bag.
Her notebook is inside.
We were just nearby.
If there's anything else...
Wait...
Has Anna been getting along with you?
She tells me nothing about school.
She's okay.
But she's very quiet.
Hey, don't.
We're just a bit loud.
Well, take care.
Ever the worrywart, your mother.
Mother...?
She's probably a hermit at school.
It's true that stress can
trigger asthma attacks.
Meanwhile, my husband's
off on a business trip.
Maybe he and I are
partly to blame, too.
12 years old...
It's a difficult age.
Have you noticed anything about her?
She...always has an ordinary face.
Ordinary face?
I'm sorry.
Like she won't show her emotions...
She used to be more expressive.
But these days, I don't even know...
Maybe it's because
we're not related by blood.
You may want to send her
somewhere to get better
"7:03 Departure for KUSHIRO"
Say, Anna...
Do you remember Uncle and Aunt Oiwa?
The air is very clean
where they live.
It'll help your condition
to spend some time there.
I can't go with you,
but they'll take care of you.
Be a good girl, eat well,
and come back nice and happy.
She whines like a goat.
Oh, here she is.
Anna.
No, but Auntie told me
all about you.
I hope I'm not much trouble.
Thank you for having me.
Our pleasure.
Auntie?
She means Yoriko.
Get on in. Sorry it's
a bit of a clunker.
Sorry it's tight in here.
I don't mind at all.
This area's changed since I was
last here. All these new shops.
Where we're headed
is a nice, relaxing place.
But since the highway was built,
people stopped coming.
They still haven't fixed that pothole!
I hear you have asthma?
The wind here will
fix you up in no time.
What's that over there?
Oh, that's a silo.
It's for storing feed for livestock.
Hasn't been used in decades, though.
Now the village kids
use it for dares.
They say there are ghosts there.
Dear, please!
Best to stay away from there.
Look, that's our house over there.
Here, mind taking this in?
What's this?
Why would you accept this?
He's always accepting gifts
without thinking...
Our kids are all grown up
and moved out.
Make yourself at home.
Let's see, these go where...
Excuse me.
You must think it's an odd house.
No, it's a lovely home.
No need for flattery.
Your room's upstairs.
It was my daughter's room.
It'd be sad to clear everything,
so I left it as it was.
She's a yoga teacher in Tokyo now.
I'm thinking of trying it myself.
Oh, and feel free to use
the closet and shelves.
Oh, thank you.
"Write me how things are,
whatever you please. Yoriko"
Postcards, how quaint!
You should write her.
Come here for a sec!
Coming!
See you later.
Smells like a stranger's house.
Feels nice.
I've arrived safely.
It's quite nice here.
Mr. and Mrs. Oiwa are
both very kind.
"To Yoriko Sasaki"
These are delicious.
Um, I'm going to the post office.
Won't you try this?
Okay, I'll save it for dessert.
"SHORTCUT"
This is the shortcut?
Wait, I need to drop off a letter.
Hey, who's that?
Why is it...
That mansion feels familiar.
I wonder if anyone lives here.
Excuse me...
What a big house.
I guess there's no one here.
Oh, no...
Thank you.
He's a bear.
Or maybe a sea lion.
Sounds like an adventure!
Completely different
in high tide, isn't it?
It's the power of the moon.
But imagine that, Toichi giving
a girl a ride on his boat.
He's actually a good guy.
Just not much of a talker.
You should ask him for a ride again.
Ask him for a ride.
I will.
But it's best you stay away
from The Marsh House.
How come?
Not again!
I'm getting some wine.
Looked like no one lives there.
Not now, anyway.
Used to be a vacation home
for some foreigners.
Then it changed hands a few times.
But it's been vacant
for a while now.
I see...
Someone's there.
Have you finished them yet?
What Mrs. Kadoya asked for.
Oh...Almost done.
Yes.
Just finish them already...
Thank you.
Yoriko was worried about her,
but she looks fine to me.
As long as she's having fun
and eating well.
That's for sure.
Now begin!
Toichi the mute!
Toichi who only talks once a decade!
Hey, I said we're not going
there until later!
Perhaps we'll hear
from you next time!
I'm going out.
Wait, Anna.
I have a little errand,
so hold on.
Yes.
"I'm allergic to that lady," he says!
But Mrs. Kadoya's been
wanting to meet you.
Their daughter Nobuko
is a year older than you.
Nobuko is at cram school today.
This must be Anna.
Nice to meet you.
Ah, so you draw, I see?
Show me next time.
No, I'm not very good.
Oh, you should go to the Tanabata
Festival with Nobuko tomorrow.
Great idea! I should still
have my daughter's yukata.
You can wear it to the festival.
But...
Yes.
I'll let Nobuko know.
Now come in.
Uh, actually I...
Oh, you're going sketching.
Go ahead!
She'll look great!
- This one, too.
- Got it.
I won't look good in it.
None of her business.
He's not here.
- Bye.
- See you tomorrow.
The tide is out.
Again.
I hate festivals.
Wait for me.
- Here's some candy.
- Thanks.
Mom forces her tastes on me.
It's awful.
What? No way!
So Anna, where are you from?
From Sapporo.
Sure, sure.
Not much to choose from
here in the boonies.
Why'd you come out here?
What is it?
I'll warn him next time.
Will my wish come true?
Can I have a candle?
Here you go.
Write your wish on this.
My wish...
Ow!
Sorry about that.
Anna!
Hey, where were you?
I was looking for you.
Oh, your wish.
Let's see...
"I wish for a normal life everyday."
Uh, Well...
Hey, your eye color!
What?
Leave me alone!
You fat pig!
Fat...
Uh...l mean...
I see what you mean by normal.
But there's no use
pretending to be normal.
After all, you look
like just what you are.
Okay, now let's drop it.
You should join us next...
Anna!
Hey, watch it!
Like just what I am...
Ugly, stupid,
moody,
unpleasant...
That's why...
I hate myself.
That's why everyone...
Still talking about that?
It'll be best for her if you two...
I better get home.
Did someone row it here?
It's stuck!
Throw me the rope!
The rope?
Hurry!
Are you okay?
Yeah. Oh, um...
Are you a real person?
Don't let anyone hear.
You look like the girl
I saw in my dreams.
Dreams?
Thanks.
It's not a dream.
What's your name?
Anna.
I'm desperate to get to know you.
What about you?
Yes.
Have you seen me before?
Often.
I've been here for ages...
Look at this, the marsh at night.
Madam.
I know.
By the way, where's that child?
Was she not in her room?
I need to get back.
Yes.
Usually I'm in bed by this hour.
Come on, I'll row you back.
So it was your boat.
Yes, I left it for you on purpose.
But I thought you'd
row a little better.
I know. So did I.
You're my precious secret.
I haven't told anyone about you,
and I won't.
If someone finds out,
they'll only spoil it.
Please, promise me.
That we'll remain a secret.
Forever.
Yes.
It'll be our secret.
Forever.
It was awful. She came home
crying her eyes out!
She called my daughter a fat pig!
Fat pig?
Now bring her here.
Seems she's not home yet.
She's a delinquent,
out and about this late!
You two are at fault, too!
Better keep an eye on her.
No, thank you.
What if something happens
to one of the kids?
Don't get so riled up.
She is not a delinquent.
Ah, she's home.
Anna.
Were you listening?
Don't you worry.
You two'll make up.
Now take a bath and have dinner.
It hardly matters.
But "fat pig" is a bit harsh.
That's for sure.
It's not that funny.
Auntie, worrying like always.
Anna! Watermelon!
Anna?
Two hours until high tide...
Hop in. Time for a picnic.
I brought juice and cookies.
That's right.
Let's go across the marsh.
You're very good at rowing.
You need rowing lessons.
Come here.
It's easy.
Remember I said last night
that you're my precious secret?
I remember. And you're my secret.
I'm glad.
Hey!
Good, you're doing well.
But I don't even know
your name yet.
I hadn't told you?
Marnie.
I thought you already knew.
That's dangerous.
Go ahead, just row.
There's so much I want
to know about you.
But I want to find out slowly.
Slowly, by myself, as we go along.
Okay.
I'll tell you what we'll do.
We'll ask each other
three questions a night.
Great.
Question one. Why are you
here in this village?
The doctor said I should go somewhere
with clean air for a while.
If there's no attack, I'm fine.
So I'm staying here with
Auntie's relatives, the Oiwas.
It's my turn to ask now.
Do you live in that mansion?
Ever since I was two.
With Nan and the maids.
It's juice.
Where are your parents?
They only come here sometimes.
They're busy with work.
Question two. Who's Auntie?
My guardian.
What do you mean?
I'll explain sometime.
It's my turn now.
How come?
Oh, it's nothing.
Just curious what it's like
to have siblings.
I know, it'd be fun to imagine that.
All right, question three.
What's it like living at the Oiwas?
At the Oiwas?
Huh...
How strange...
I can't...
remember...
Marnie?
Anna!
There you are.
I wondered where you went.
Marnie?
I looked all over for you.
You just disappeared.
I was just trying to
answer your question.
Wait...
What was it?
I need to go soon. Today is...
Oh, I know!
Don't worry.
I have a great idea.
It's true.
That's hard to believe.
Sorry, did you wait long?
I had trouble getting away.
Marnie.
What do you think?
It's pretty.
I borrowed Nan's shawl.
I'll be scolded again.
This won't work.
Don't worry, I spoke to Father.
Young lady.
I believe it is past your bedtime.
And who might this be?
She is wearing my shawl.
Upstairs!
Wait right there!
You must be up to no good again.
You go that way.
Marnie!
Why you little...
Marnie! Open it!
You'll grow up to be
a lousy adult!
Everyone, we have a
lovely flower girl here.
She'll be pretty like her mother.
May I please have
one of those flowers?
My mother.
Hello, dear little witch.
That woman there's the real witch.
I want only one, for good luck.
Will someone kindly pay
for my flower?
If it is the witch's command...
Then I'll have one, too.
- Here.
- For superb luck.
Ah, it's begun.
Oh, she ran away.
Come take one each, for luck!
Young lady.
To your health.
Thank you.
Wine?
Awake now?
L---
Drunkard.
Who was that?
Which one?
The one dancing with you.
You mean Kazuhiko?
An old friend.
He's a good dancer.
So are you.
Now let's dance, you and I.
Just follow my lead.
Look for me again.
And don't tell anyone. Promise.
I know.
Hey, wait...
Is that...?
It's the girl with the Oiwas.
I see. Hope you find the other shoe.
It must be somewhere.
I'll go look.
Used to always lose mine.
There's a bunch buried
in the mud flats.
Don't compare her to you.
I should have
my daughter's old shoes.
I'll get them out.
Thank you.
Marnie...
Wow.
Not only are they big,
they're delicious, too.
You're good with the knife.
Auntie teaches me all the time.
You're so polite
and well-behaved.
My daughter could learn from you.
Passing behind you.
I remember when you first
came to Yoriko's place.
She was ecstatic.
She wanted to make up for the
five years she didn't have with you.
So she taught you things,
like knife skills.
But she worries too much.
Oh, I shouldn't share this
about your mother.
No, I understand.
You know, Yoriko sent us
tons of photos of you.
I'll show you later.
Hey, look.
Found the wind chime
I made on our honeymoon.
To survive the summer.
Your hair's getting long.
Shall I give you a haircut?
That would be a disaster.
Mar...nie...'?
Look for me again.
How could I nearly
forget about Marnie?
Marnie...
Marnie!
May I?
Sure.
I see you draw, too.
She was a great girl.
Yes, she is.
But I haven't seen her in a week.
I wonder if she's upset that I forgot.
If she's a friend,
talk to her and you'll be fine.
Say, will you take a look?
Sure.
No, it's wonderful.
I'm in love with The Marsh House.
What about you?
I'm Anna. I love it, too.
Better hurry and finish your drawing...
before the new folks move in.
The renovations are under way.
Oh, thank you. Appreciate it.
All right, coming.
Are you Marnie?
Come.
I hadn't seen the front before.
It's a lot cleaner now,
but not done yet.
Brought a friend, huh?
Choose your slippers.
Secret?
Hey!
Sorry, make yourself at home.
Thank you.
Yes, we're still in
the middle of renovation.
This room...
Upstairs.
This hasn't been renovated yet.
Here, this is my room.
Really...
It's a cute room.
It used to be your room, right?
You're...Marnie, right?
Me? No, no!
See, that's where I always see you.
I've seen you many times.
No, no.
That can't be.
When I said Marnie earlier,
you were surprised.
Rather, why do you know Marnie?
I found it behind the shelf.
That's right. Your diary.
Marnie!
I'll pour you some
Queen Mary, your favorite.
I'll be back.
"Last night I went for
a row in my nightie."
"The marsh and the moon
were very pretty at night."
I shall do it again.
June 8th. A party!
Father, Mother and many of their
friends came. It was such fun.
I went outside from the sunroom
and danced with a flower girl.
But...
Nan locked me in my room
because of last night.
So there won't be any
midnight rows for a bit.
See, it's you, isn't it?
No.
Marnie is...
someone I made up.
An imaginary girl, only in my mind.
But this is Marnie's diary.
It's as if she really lived here.
So you're not Marnie?
She's just imaginary?
That's right.
I thought you were Marnie,
back for her diary...
I'm Anna. I came from
Sapporo to get better.
I'm Sayaka.
I'm from Tokyo.
But if she was imaginary,
why is her name the same?
I don't know.
Marnie must be real.
I'm going to investigate.
Say, Marnie...
Who are you?
Is that me?
Marnie?
Marnie!
Wait, that one's not done yet...
Wow, you draw well.
Oh, thanks...
I've never had anyone
draw me before. How nice!
I missed you.
I kept calling you in my heart.
Me, too.
Come to my room.
Come to my room, Marnie.
I can't go far from the mansion.
Okay then, we'll go
wherever you want.
You know a lot about mushrooms.
Father taught me when I was little.
I once brought home
three bags full of mushrooms.
The look on Mother's face!
What's wrong?
So quiet all of a sudden.
You're very lucky.
I wish I was you.
Talk to me.
I'm...
a foster child.
My real parents died
when I was little.
My grandmother, too.
I know they didn't
die on purpose, but...
sometimes I feel like...
I can't forgive them...
for leaving me all alone.
I'm jealous of you.
You're lucky to be a foster child.
If you had no relatives,
then the folks who took
you in as a daughter
must be truly kindhearted people.
Then I'll tell you a big secret.
It's about my foster parents.
They're good to me and they're kind.
I'm not their real child, yet they
raised me, which I appreciate.
But you see, I saw it one day.
They're paid money for it.
Money?
I found a letter from the government.
It said they were increasing
the subsidy for me.
I don't care!
They wouldn't get money if
I were their real child.
They get paid because
I'm not their real child.
Even worse...
they hide it from me.
I see.
But that doesn't mean
Auntie doesn't love you.
None of the other families
receive money. Just us!
She always looks worried
that I might find out.
And I hate myself for
thinking like this.
L...just can't...believe...
in anything anymore.
Just know that I love you.
I love you more than
any girl I've ever known.
Then you tell me your secret next.
It was long ago that I went
mushrooming with Father.
Nowadays, I hardly see my parents.
Mother's usually travelling.
Because of work,
Father's home only twice a year.
Usually, Nan and the twin maids
are the only ones home.
And me.
I slip out while they're gossiping.
And look how free I get to be!
It's lovely when
my parents come home.
They host parties!
Like the other day.
With my amazing parents
and many people there,
it's delightful.
I get to wear new dresses
and dance, too.
That's when I'm sure I'm
the luckiest girl in the world.
I see.
Tell me, Anna. Will you
be my friend forever?
Yes.
I'm your friend forever.
Right?
Nan's always in a bad mood.
She yanks me by the arm,
brushes my hair very hard...
No one thinks I'm being bullied.
But it really hurts.
Enough to cry.
The maids love to frighten me.
They threatened me
all the time.
"Naughty kids get shut in the silo
"where ghosts suck out
their souls," they said.
You mean, the silo on the hill?
Once, they actually took me there.
They dragged me
all the way to the silo.
I thought I'd die of fright.
Just as we got there, the sky
went dark and the thunder came.
The maids were terrified,
so we didn't go inside.
I can endure anything else.
Anything but the silo.
I never heard such a terrible thing!
I hope the maids and Nan
get struck by lightning!
Hasn't anyone ever
tried to frighten you?
Never. Definitely not on purpose.
You're lucky.
I wish I was you.
Our castle...
Poor Marnie.
I love you the most, too.
More than anyone I've known.
Thank you.
Funny, it's like we traded places.
How true.
The tide's coming in.
Hey, let's go to the silo together.
The ghosts must be a lie.
Let's go make sure.
Tomorrow...No, let's go right now.
I don't care who Marnie really is.
I just want to help her.
Are you okay, Marnie?
Yes, I'm sure I'll be
all right if I'm with you...
Kazuhiko.
Anna!
Perfect timing! I found it!
The rest of the diary.
Come to my place.
Marnie...
I'm sorry. Another time.
What? But it's a major discovery...
It's going to rain!
Who is it?
Is someone there?
Marnie!
So you did go ahead.
Don't scare me like that.
Marnie.
Kazuhiko!
I'm frightened.
I heard somebody below.
I thought I'd die of fright.
Kazuhiko...
Anna...Anna!
I don't want to be humiliated.
Oh, Anna...
You do have courage.
You came here.
Let's go home.
Wait!
It's just the wind. Let's go.
We'll go home together.
Anna, come back here.
Anna!
We made it up. I'm sure
we can make it down.
I'll go first, so follow me.
No, don't leave me!
No!
Marnie!
Let's go over there.
I'm cold...So cold...
Oh Anna, I'm scared...
I'm scared...
You did well, Marnie.
Are you okay?
Kazuhiko!
I thought you'd never come.
.---.---
Let's go home.
Marnie?
Marnie!
Marnie...You left me behind!
Even you!
Kazuhiko...Kazuhiko...
Kazuhiko's all over this diary.
"Kazuhiko is trying to
take me to the silo."
Silo...
Yes?
Mom cooked some corn.
Wait!
Why go out on a night like this?
My friend might be caught in the rain.
What if she gets pneumonia?
Is that...
Anna!
Are you okay?
So cruel...
Anna?
So cruel, Marnie...
She has high fever!
I'll go get help.
Anna.
Anna?
Anna...
How's she doing?
Her fever's not coming down.
She did get a shot earlier.
I see.
So cruel...
Marnie, how could you?
I won't forgive you.
Leaving me behind without a word.
Anna! My dear Anna!
Marnie! How could you
leave me behind?
Why did you betray me?
I'm sorry, I didn't mean
to leave you all alone.
But...
But at that moment,
you weren't there.
What do you mean?
Oh, Anna, I...
I can't stay here any longer.
I have to say goodbye to you.
So please, Anna,
please say you forgive me!
Anna...
Of course, I forgive you!
I love you, Marnie!
And I won't forget you!
I'll never forget you! Ever!
Anna.
Sayaka's here for you.
Thanks.
You can see her in your room.
"I'd love to show you. - Anna"
Sayaka.
Here, a get-well gift.
Thanks.
Also...
This is what made me think
you might be at the silo.
The rest of the diary
you promised to read.
I impressed myself.
I found a clue in this painting
that was behind the cupboard.
Maybe I'm psychic.
Turn it over.
Hisako!
Please, will you tell us
about Marnie?
But...
it's a rather sad story.
I'm ready for it.
It was a long time ago.
I used to play at
The Marsh House often.
Let me see.
This is Daddy. Isn't he dashing?
Her glamorous parents and
their extravagant parties.
But the truth is,
she was being neglected.
Goodbye, Marnie.
Seems even the maids
were bullying her.
That's awful!
And married Kazuhiko,
her childhood friend.
He was there to support her.
I'm glad. So Kazuhiko was a good man.
Two years later, Emily was born.
At last in the warm household she'd
always wanted, Marnie was happy.
I didn't see Marnie for
many years after that.
The next time was...
a few years after Kazuhiko
had died of an illness.
By then,
Marnie was in a sanatorium
due to the shock of his death.
Sanatorium?
A place where you go to get better.
What happened to Emily?
Marnie's parents had died,
leaving no one to look after her.
So for elementary school,
she was sent to a boarding school.
By the time she returned at age 13,
she'd become a different person.
Emily!
She was willful and independent.
But still resented her
for sending her away.
I want you to live the way
you wish, but...
They never did make up after that.
I've never thought of you
as a mother.
Emily ran away and
soon got married.
She was expecting, you see.
But...
One day, Emily and her husband
died in a car accident.
I heard Marnie took their child in.
She was determined to never
let this child be lonely.
But...
she never got over losing Emily.
She became very ill,
and died the next year.
That was about ten years ago.
I'm sorry, it's a sad story.
No, thank you very much.
Marnie adored that mansion.
She loved seeing the marsh
from her window.
She said it felt like
the birds spoke to her.
She had a lonely life,
but she lived it fully.
Always with a smile,
determined to be happy.
So you've met Marnie, too.
Wish we could've played more, Anna.
The plan was always
just for the summer.
Will you come again next summer?
I'm sure I will. I'll write you.
I'll write you, too.
Good, it's for the best.
I haven't told my family.
Let's keep it our secret.
How funny...
Marnie brought us together.
That's true.
Marnie...
The girl trapped behind
the blue window...
That was long ago.
Ah, now I want to
read it all over again.
I'll loan you Volume 2.
Anna!
Auntie!
Anna...
Sorry, sorry.
Auntie's here.
Ah, Yoriko, you're here.
She's doing well,
and even made a friend.
Oh, no. We didn't do
anything at all.
It was like having
our own daughter back.
She's welcome anytime.
Thank you.
Let's talk inside.
I'm impressed you didn't
call us this time.
I'm all packed.
Anna.
Yes?
There's something
I need to tell you.
We receive monthly subsidies
to cover your expenses.
We receive money.
But believe me...
Whether or not we receive money,
it doesn't change our love for you.
I already knew.
Anna!
I've been looking at
the photos you sent.
And found this picture.
Do you remember?
When you first came,
you wouldn't let it go.
I was told at the orphanage
it belonged to your grandmother.
"My beloved home - Marnie"
Marnie!
So that's who she was.
Anna.
And so I was in
the silo all night.
I was very frightened.
That's when your grandpa came.
He encouraged me,
saying I did well.
I've overcome many
frightening things.
And so will you, Anna.
You're my one and only grandchild.
Grandma...
Excuse me.
Anna.
I'm sorry for what I said.
Don't skip trash pickup next year.
A friend?
Maybe.
Hisako!
Anna.
Is that right?
But your face tells me
something good happened.
Good.
Um, this is my mother.
Thank you for being kind to Anna.
Oh no, it was my pleasure.
Goodbye.
Thank you very much.
Yeah, I'll tell you later.
I promise I'll tell you.
Toichi! Sayaka! Goodbye!
Voices
Sara Takatsuki Kasumi Arimura
Susumu Terajima Toshie Negishi
Ryoko Moriyama Kazuko Yoshiyuki
Nanako Matsushima Hitomi Kuroki
Executive Producer
Toshio Suzuki
Based on the novel "When Marnie Was There"
by Joan G. Robinson
Screenplay by Keiko Niwa,
Masashi Ando and Hiromasa Yonebayashi
Music Takatsugu Muramatsu
Theme Song Priscilla Ahn
Supervising Animator
Masashi Ando
Production Designer
YoheiTaneda
English Subtitles by Taro Goto
Subtitle Production by Aura
Production Koji Hoshino
Studio Ghibli
Producer Yoshiaki Nishimura
Directed by Hiromasa Yonebayashi
"The End"